TheChaosLegion
l want to shine on you,
and always like that dazzling sun.
l will defend you
from all the darkness.
This is the truth from my heart.
lf only our hearts could connect,
l could get you to believe me.
Even if you can't
see it now, don't lose it.
Your kindness won't be in vain.
You'll be carried aloft by the wind
to somewhere that isn't here.
You'll cross the sea and cross time,
and l know you'll blossom one day.
Whatever the day,
l'll be there for you.
l hope l can watch over you
like the sun for all time.
This is the truth from my heart.
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
～♪
（二ノ妃(にのきさき)）
ここに身を寄せて以来―
Since coming here,
l have been given the opportunity...
生まれて初めて 家事というものを
たしなむようになりました
...to enjoy housework
for the first time in my life.
これを
Look.
世に言う母の手に
近づいてきたとは思いませんか？
Have they not come to resemble what
people refer to as "mothers' hands"?
l see that you have no intention
of speaking a harsh word to me.
（シュガ）どうあっても―
私を ののしっては
くださらないのですね
lt was because of my incompetence
that Prince Chagum...
私が至らなかったために
チャグム皇子は…
そなたは ざんげをするために
ここへ参られておるのか？
Did you come here so that
you could repent your sins?
To this day, l still believe
that Chagum is alive.
私は 今でも チャグムが
生きていると信じています
そなたの目には―
l expect that l appear as a
foolish mother in your eyes.
さぞかし
愚かな母と映ることでしょう
But l simply cannot believe that...
ですが 私には
どうしても あの者が―
...that person would die
without completing her promised task.
約束の途中で倒れるような人間には
思えないのです
（シュガ）“あの者”とは
くだんの女用心棒のことですか？
By "that person," you are referring
to the female bodyguard?
l saw in her eyes an indomitable
strength of will and magical power.
あの者の目には―
何事にも屈せぬ強い意志と
魔力があった
シュガ殿
Shuga, if you wish to repay what
you see as an obligation toward me...
もし そなたに 私に報いたいという
思いがあるなら―
...will you go and verify with your
own eyes whether Chagum still lives?
チャグムが生きていることを―
その目で
確かめては くださらぬか？
lf you do that, l will be able
to live here in contentment.
さすれば 私も
ここで心おきなく生きていける
l once believed that a strength similar
to hers dwelled in your own eyes.
以前は そなたの目にも―
あの者と同じような力が
宿っていると思ったのは―
Or was l mistaken in that belief?
私の思い違いでしたか？
Episode 9
Shuga
Thirsts
Grandpa! l need some rice pounded!
（ガキ大将）
じいさん！ 米 ついてくれよ
あれ？ 誰だ？ お前
Huh? Who are you?
Whose kid are you?
どこの子だ？
何だ？ お前 しゃべれないのか？
What's your problem? Can't you talk?
Who are you kids?
（バルサ）何だい？ あんたたち
（ガキ大将）あっ…
No, who are you?
あんたこそ誰だよ？
じいさんは留守かい？
ls the old man out?
l need him to pound
some rice for me.
米 ついてほしいんだけどなあ
Ah, l see. So our water mill
had some customers.
（バルサ）なるほどね
うちの水車にも
お客がいたってわけだ
Fine, come on in.
いいよ 入りな
（ガキ大将）おう
Right.
First, we shall establish a new
steel office which will oversee...
（サグム）まず
鉄の製造と流通をつかさどる―
...the production
and distribution of iron.
鋼役なる役どころを新たに設けます
Only those goods that have met
this office's strict standards...
そこで厳選した良質な品にのみ―
...will be allowed to carry
the palace crest.
宮の刻印を押すことを認める
Trade with other countries will also
be conducted through this office.
他国との取り引きも
この鋼役を通して行い―
もちろん その利益の一部は
職人へ行き渡るように計らいます
Part of the profits will, of course,
be disbursed to the craftsmen.
ln doing this, l believe we will be able
to maintain the highest level of quality...
そうすれば 品質の維持を
徹底することができ―
...and at the same time keep
the craftsmen's morale high.
同時に 職人たちの士気を
高めることもできましょう
（帝(みかど)）よく分かった
Very well, l am convinced.
You have considered every detail.
確かに筋は通っておる
l will present your plan at
the next council meeting.
早速 次回の評定に かけるとしよう
異論はないな？
（聖導師(せいどうし)）もちろんです
You have no objections, l take it?
None, Sire.
Thank you, Majesty.
ありがとうございます
時に 父上
lncidentally, Father...
l understand that Chagum's
personal effects are being collected?
チャグムの身の回りの品を
集めておられるとか
Yes.
（サグム）それらの品を
極秘裏のうちに焼くことで―
Gakai informs me that you hope to
fully lift the water demon's curse...
水妖(すいよう)の呪いを
完全に払おうとのお考えと―
...by burning all of these items
in the strictest secrecy.
ガカイより聞きました
（サグム）
ですが 私の知るかぎり―
To my knowledge, however...
...it is proving ever more difficult to ensure
that the entire court holds their silence.
宮中(きゅうちゅう)全ての口に戸を立てるのは
難しくなりつつあります
もし よろしければ その任 全て
私に任せては いただけませぬか？
lf it is agreeable to Your Majesty...
...perhaps l might be entrusted to
carry out this duty solely on my own?
いいだろう かまわん よきに計らえ
As you wish. l have no objections.
Do as you see fit.
（聖導師）
実に立派になられましたな
He has grown to be
an exemplary prince.
After Prince Chagum's death,
he seemed rather melancholy.
チャグム皇子が
亡くなられたときは―
かなり塞いでおられたようでしたが
（帝）うむ…
もう すっかり立ち直ったようだ
Yes.
He appears to be his old self again.
l am certain that is due in no small part
to the efforts of his tutor-governor.
カシヅキによるところも
大きいのではないか？
Thank you for your
generous words, Sire.
ありがたき お言葉にございます
lt looks like the sign of the great drought
will remain for quite some time.
（星読み１）今回の乾ノ相(かわきのそう)
まだまだ続きそうですね
Yes. According to a rumor that
l accidentally overheard recently...
（星読み２）うん そのことで 私が
小耳にはさんだウワサによると…
When you were relieved
as tutor-governor...
カシヅキの任を解かれたとたん―
宵の勤めが始まるときも
忘れてしまったか
...did you also forget what time
our evening duties are set to begin?
（星読み３）おかげで
こちらに しわ寄せが来ているのだ
Thanks to you,
our workload is now heavier.
You're setting a bad example
for the apprentices!
そのようなことでは
下級の者に 示しがつかぬぞ
ln spite of your zeal for your work...
仕事熱心なわりには
肝心なものが見えておらぬようだ
...you seem to be overlooking
what is truly important.
どういう意味だ！
What do you mean by that?
ls that supposed to be an insult?
我々を侮辱するのか！
And what if it is?
だとしたら どうなんだ？
Who does he think he is?
何だ？ あの態度は
lt's not like he knows
any more than we do...
何も知らぬくせに
How can they be so optimistic?
（シュガ）なぜ
ああまで楽観的でいられるのだ？
They are so singlemindedly
focused on purification...
チャグム皇子の犠牲も忘れ―
...that they have forgotten
Prince Chagum's sacrifice.
汚れ払いなどに躍起になって
（ガカイ）モタモタするな 行くぞ
うん？
Stop dawdling. Let's go.
Master Gakai?
ガカイ様 私の部屋で何を？
What are you doing in my quarters?
君たち…
What's that you two have in...
それは？
Those are...
We are going to lift
the water demon's curse!
水妖の呪いを払うのだ
What? But we are star readers! That
makes us no better than magic weavers!
そんな！
それでは まるで
星読みではなく 呪術師では…
チャグム皇子のものは 全てを―
Our orders are to bring all of...
...Prince Chagum's belongings
to Crown Prince Sagum.
サグム殿下の下に
集めよとのお達しだ
あっ… サグム殿下が…
To Crown Prince Sagum?
あすの朝 一ノ宮(いちのみや)に お届けしろ
（見習いたち）分かりました
Deliver them to lchinomiya Palace
tomorrow morning.
Yes, sir.
Wait a moment!
Doing that will accomplish nothing!
待ってください
そんなことをしても…
Are you trying to comfort yourself by
looking at the late prince's belongings?
亡き皇子の遺品を眺めて
己を慰めるのか！ 恥を知れ！
You should be ashamed!
Hand them over!
それを よこすんだ！
You mustn't!
（シュガ）ダメです！
（ガカイ）この！
You mustn't!
Why, you...
Please, you must listen to me!
（シュガ）私の話を…
（ガカイ）くどいぞ！ よこさぬか！
l've had enough of you! Give me that!
Master, let go of me!
（シュガ）離してください！
（ガカイ）うわっ！
l'm so sorry...
申し訳ございません
Are you injured?
おケガは？
下がれ
Leave us.
Uh...
下がれ！
Leave us!
l am sorely disappointed in you.
お前には失望した
There will be repercussions for this.
処罰は覚悟しておけよ
（宮仕え）聖導師様は 謹慎処分を
お申しつけになられたようです
Apparently, the master star reader has
ordered him placed under house arrest.
当然じゃ
That is to be expected.
However, Master Shuga does not
appear to be the least bit penitent.
（宮仕え）ですが シュガ様に
反省のご様子はなく―
なんでも 与えられた私室を
自ら返上し―
l am told that he has voluntarily
relinquished his private quarters...
...and has instead taken up residence
in the star reader apprentices' dormitory.
星読み見習いの大部屋に
入られたそうです
l presume you have
heard what happened.
話は聞いているんだろ？
ふだんどおりに したまえ
Just go about your normal routine.
Master Shuga. Crown Prince Sagum
requests your presence.
（宮仕え）シュガ様
サグム殿下が お呼びでございます
殿下が？
The crown prince?
Moribito Guardian of the Spirit
l hear detailed accounts of Your Highness'
deeds in every corner of the court.
（シュガ）殿下の ご活躍ぶり―
宮中の端においても
事細かに聞き及んでおります
They are nothing compared to
what l am hearing about you.
そなたのウワサには遠く及ばぬ
Here in lchinomiya Palace, not a day
goes by in which your name is not spoken.
わが一ノ宮でも
お前の名が挙がらぬ日はない
だが 聞けば
どれも そなたらしからぬ話ばかり
But it is hard to believe that these
rumors could possibly be about you.
With all due respect, Highness, the matter
regarding the late prince's belongings...
恐れながら 例の遺品の件こそ
殿下らしからぬ行為と存じます
lt does not strike me
as something that you would do.
Not a day goes by in which
smoke does not rise...
一ノ宮の裏庭から
煙の上らぬ日はございません
...from the gardens behind
lchinomiya Palace.
l respected you from the
bottom of my heart as a man...
殿下は 第一皇子である前に―
...who was a caring older brother first,
and was the first prince second.
弟思いの立派な兄であると―
私は 心より
尊敬申し上げておりました
However, it seems that
l was wrong about you.
ですが
私の思い違いだったようですね
Look.
見よ
lt happened just inside the forest there.
ちょうど あの林の中じゃ
（サグム）チャグムは
動物のことを実によく覚えておった
Chagum had such a keen memory
for facts regarding animals.
That day, his sharp eye spotted a bird
in flight that he had read about in a book.
あの日も図鑑に載っていた鳥が
飛んでいるのを目ざとく見つけた
We remembered the book saying that
this rare bird preyed upon flying frogs...
その珍しい鳥が―
飛び跳ねるカエルを
餌にすると―
図鑑に
書いてあったことを思い出し―
２人して 片っ端から
空に石を投げたりしてのう
So we both threw aloft
every rock that we could find.
石の重みに
耐えられなかったのだろう
Perhaps it was unable to bear
the weight of the stones...
無邪気な いたずらとはいえ
愚かな行いであった
lt may have been an innocent prank,
but it was a foolish act all the same.
それを宮に連れ帰って
手当してやろうと言いだしたのは―
lt was Chagum who suggested
that we bring it to the palace...
チャグムだった
...and nurse it back to health.
The bird was discovered by Father.
その鳥が父上に見つかってな
鳥の羽が
余の ぜんそくによくないと―
He scolded Chagum harshly, saying that
the bird's feathers were bad for my asthma.
チャグムが ひどく叱られた
Surely you remember
what you did then.
あのとき そなたが
何をしたか覚えておろう？
余は 今でも覚えておる
l remember it as if it were yesterday.
そなたは臆することなく
こう申した
Undaunted by him,
you said the following...
“帝は過保護すぎる”
Your Majesty is being overprotective.
“むしろ
傷ついた小さな命をいたわり―”
On the contrary, perhaps by showing
concern for small, wounded lives...
...and by caring for the animals
and plants of the outside world...
“外界の動物や植物を
慈しむことで―”
...not only will a sound mind
and body be nurtured...
“健やかな心と体が養われ―”
“ひいては 民の上に立つ者に必要な
素養が培われるのではないか”とな
...but perhaps those qualities vital in
leaders of men will also be cultivated.
Apparently, the mikado was quite
taken aback by what you said.
帝は 大層 驚かれたそうだが―
But l am told that it was this incident
that caused the master star reader...
あの一件によって
聖導師は そなたを―
二ノ(にの)カシヅキに使命したと
聞いている
...to make you the
second tutor-governor.
lt is no wonder.
当然じゃ
それだけの魅力と信念が
あのころの そなたには あった
Such was the magnetism and
conviction that you had back then.
As you did just now when you offered
me such frank and sincere criticism.
ちょうど今
余に苦言を呈したようにな
No one suspects me.
誰も疑っておらぬ
折り目正しい皇太子は
宮での信頼も厚いのじゃ
The courteous crown prince
has the complete trust of the court.
Then you did this so that you
could protect his belongings?
それでは
殿下は遺品を守るために…
Here.
さあ
l shall leave them
in your care, Highness.
それは 殿下にお預けいたします
私には もう必要ございません
l no longer have need of them.
l see.
そうか 余はな ずっと
チャグムが羨ましかったのじゃ
You know, l was always
jealous of Chagum.
帝となったチャグム―
How l wish l could have seen
Chagum as mikado...
そして それに仕える
聖導師シュガの姿というのも―
...and you serving at his side
as master star reader.
見てみたかったな
Highness...
殿下…
（シュガ）
今の私が やるべきことは―
What l ought to be doing right now...
...is not gazing into the heavens
lamenting the death of the prince.
ただ空を見上げて
皇子の死を嘆くのではなく―
皇子の尊い犠牲にもかかわらず―
But rather uncovering why the
sign of the great drought...
乾ノ相が晴れぬ原因を
突き止めることだったのだ
...has not disappeared in spite
of the prince's noble sacrifice!
Go on and join those other children.
（バルサ）仲間に入れてもらいなよ
友達を作るいい機会じゃないか
lt's the perfect chance for you
to make some friends, right?
余は別に 子供と遊びたいなどと…
あっ
l have no real desire
to play with children...
Oh, just get out there.
いいから行っといで
（チャグム）うわっ！
Excuse me, what are you doing?
あの… 何をしておるのだ？
（ガキ大将）何だ？ お前
You're kidding, right?
We're racing to see
whose leaf boat is the fastest.
誰のささ舟が 一番速いか
競争してんだよ
ささ舟？
Leaf boats?
You want to race, too?
（ガキ大将）お前もやるか？
作り方は知ってんだろ？
You do know how to make a boat, right?
Try making one yourself.
自分で作ってみろよ
（タンダ）
おっ もう友達ができたのか
Oh, he's made some friends already?
Well, l can't say for sure yet.
さあ？ どうだろうね
なんだ お前
作り方も知らねえのかよ
Come on, you don't know
how to make a leaf boat?
あーあ 先にケンカのしかたを
教えてやったほうが―
Uh-oh. Do you think you should have
taught him how to fight first?
よかったんじゃないのか？
Who do you think has the harder job?
女手一つで男の子を育てるのと
男手一つで女の子を育てるのと―
A woman raising a boy on her own...
...or a man raising a girl on his own?
いったい どっちが大変だと思う？
Are you talking about Jiguro?
ジグロのこと言ってんのか？
Let me think...
そうだな…
そりゃ 当然 男が女の子を
育てるほうが苦労するだろうな
Yes, it's definitely harder
for a man to raise a girl.
The thought of being handed a girl the
same age as him sends chills up my spine.
俺が今 あのくらいの女の子を
預かることになると思ったら―
ぞっとするよ
The difference is that boys will grow up by
themselves even if you leave them alone.
所詮 男の子なんて―
ほったらかしでも
大きくなっていくものだからな
まあ もっとも
俺と出会ったころには―
Well, by the time l met you,
you were pretty much a boy anyway.
お前は もう 男同然だったけどな
さて 飯の支度をしようかね
l suppose l should start making dinner.
Really? Are you sure?
あれ？ いいのか？
（バルサ）
あんたが 今 言ったじゃないか
You said it yourself, didn't you?
He'll do just fine on his own.
あの子は
放っておいても大丈夫だよ
（女の子）
あっ！ お兄ちゃん トビカワズ！
Look, brother! A flying frog!
どこだ？
（女の子）ほら そこ！
What? Where?
See? Over there!
わあ！
Actually, its official name
is the Nayoro Flying Frog.
あれは 正式には
ナユロトビガエルっていうんだ
（ガキ大将）みんな来い！
Come on, everybody!
Four!
Five!
Six!
あっ… ダメだ！
Don't!
そんなことしちゃダメだ！
You mustn't do that!
カエルは
餌を捕ろうとして跳んでるんだ
The frogs are jumping
to try to catch their food!
lt is wrong to interfere just
to play some childish game!
だから ただの遊びで
邪魔したりしちゃダメだ！
何だよ？
What is it with you?
Come on, this isn't
fun anymore. Let's go.
あーあ なんか しらけちまったな
行こうぜ
Each location's soil samples contain
the normal amount of water...
（シュガ）どの場所の土も―
含んでいる水の量は
ふだんと変わらない
（シュガ）釣れますか？
（釣り人）ああ？
Are they biting?
What?
Oh, yes.
That is quite a catch you have there.
大漁だな
しかも 大物ばかりじゃないか
And look, nothing but big fish!
Yes, thank you for saying so.
（釣り人）
はあ おかげさまで なんとか
（シュガ）数のほうは？
魚が減ったりはしておらぬか？
What about the number?
Has the number of fish declined?
（釣り人）
いつもと変わりありませんが
No, it's no different than the usual.
あの…
魚が どうかなさいましたか？
Um... ls there something
wrong with the fish?
What about the
vegetable and fruit crops?
（シュガ）それでは
野菜や果物の収穫はどうだ？
Has the harvest been good?
出来はよいのか？
ええ
どこも おおむね豊作のようですが
Yes, it looks like everyone's
been having a bumper crop.
（シュガ）よかった
乾ノ相は遠ざかっている
Thank goodness...
The sign of the great drought is fading.
皇子の死は
無駄ではなかったということか
This means that the prince's death
was not in vain, l suppose.
This one is pretty impressive.
（タンダ）
これは なかなかのものだぞ
ハハッ これも大物だ
This one is huge, too!
You there, what is it
that you are doing?
（シュガ）
そこの人 何をしておるのだ？
l spotted these rare grasses,
and l couldn't help myself.
珍しい草を見つけたもんで つい
こいつの根っこは
腹いたに よく効く薬になるんだ
You can make an effective medicine for
stomachaches with the roots of this plant.
立派な道具ですね
（シュガ）うん？
Those are fine tools
that you have there.
Are they all yours?
（タンダ）あれ 全部あなたの？
（シュガ）ああ
Yes.
Would you mind if l
took a look at them?
見せてもらっていいかな？
（シュガ）えっ？
へえー
目盛りで計るようになってるのか
Ah, these graduations
let you measure things...
へえー
（シュガ）君…
Would you mind...
（タンダ）
これ使って 何をしていたんです？
What were you measuring
with this stuff?
ls there some reason why
you need to investigate the river?
川を調べなきゃいけない理由でも？
いや 私が調べていたのは
今後のことなのだ
No, l was investigating something
that will happen in the future.
To determine whether or not there will
be a change in the amount of water.
この先 水の量に
変化がありはしないか… とね
The amount of water?
水の量？ あっ…
Take a look.
これを
ls there something important
about that plant?
（シュガ）その草が何か？
No, not the plant.
Look. lt's a mantis egg.
（タンダ）そうじゃないよ
ほら カマキリの卵
A mantis?
カマキリ？
This one's just an empty husk now, but
the height at which a mantis lays its eggs...
こいつは もう抜け殻だけど
カマキリの卵の高さによって―
ある程度
来年の水量を知ることができるんだ
...can give you a rough idea of how much
water there will be the following year.
For instance, it's said that when eggs
are laid close to the ground like this one...
例えば こんなふうに 低い位置に
卵を産みつけた冬なんかは―
まず雪の量が
少ないと言われている
...there will be hardly
any snow that winter.
それは本当か？
ls that true?
Well, that was the case
this year, remember?
今年も そうだったでしょ？
lt's just an oral tradition among
the Yakoo, but l think it's accurate.
あくまで ヤクーの
言い伝えにすぎないけど―
当たると思うよ
ヤクーの？
（タンダ）ええ
The Yakoo?
Right.
実は 私は―
The truth is, l was worried that there
might be a shortage of water soon.
近く水不足が起こるのではないかと
危惧していたのだ
もし そなたの
言うとおりだとして―
Assuming that what you say is correct...
この川の魚は
大きく太っているようだし―
...the fish in this river are large and fat...
野菜や果物も豊作らしい
...and the fruit and vegetable
crops are abundant.
lf that's the case...
となると―
そなたの話とは
矛盾してはいないか？
...does that not contradict
what you just said?
Well, maybe not.
うーん… どうかな？
Animals gorge on food to fatten up
before they hibernate for the winter, right?
獣は冬眠する前に
餌をたくさん食べて肥えるでしょ？
Yes...
Maybe what we're seeing
is something like that.
（タンダ）それと
似たようなことなんじゃないかな
Maybe all the animals,
and even the plants...
生き物だけじゃなく 植物も―
これから訪れようとしてる状況に
備えようとしているとか
...are preparing themselves to survive a
set of conditions that will be on us soon.
lf you look at it that way, everything fits.
そう考えれば つじつまは合う
This is what you are saying, then?
つまり こういうことか
１年以内に この地に
干ばつが訪れる可能性がある
That within a year, there is a possibility
that this land will be visited by a drought?
What is it?
どうした？
（タンダ）いや…
Well, judging from your appearance,
l think you're from the court.
あなた 身なりからして
宮の方かと思いますが―
So why are you out here
investigating something like that?
どういった訳で
このようなことを？
Hey!
（船頭）おーい！
（船頭）
そこの方 お乗りにならんのかね？
Sir! Will you be needing
the boat or not?
今 参る！
l shall be right there.
それじゃ 私は これで
Well, l should be taking my leave now.
What about you?
What is your trade?
そなたこそ どういった仕事を？
薬草師です
l'm an herbologist.
（シュガ）乾ノ相が
消えていないとすると―
lf the sign of the great drought
has not disappeared...
二ノ妃が言うように―
...then perhaps Prince Chagum is still
alive somewhere, as the second queen said.
チャグム皇子は
どこかで生きているのかもしれない
lt would seem that l must begin my
investigations again from square one.
もう一度
一から調べ直す必要があるな
As l sat huddled and alone, holding
back the tears on those nights...
When it felt like l was about
to succumb to my doubts...
...there you were,
at my side before l knew it.
lt was none other than you
who was there for me.
l keep wishing, "l want to be strong."
l stumble and hurt myself again.
But because l have you to believe in,
l can get back to my feet.
l simply want to tell
my dear one, "Thank you."
At the top of my lungs,
again and again.
l call out to my precious loved one.
ls my voice reaching you?
ln this world that always changes,
human warmth never does.
l'm certain l sensed the presence
of the one that l hold dear.
～♪
Next Time
Worried about Chagum's decidedly
un-"common" demeanor...
...Balsa decides to
take drastic measures.
Next time, "Soil and Heroes."
Episode 10
Soil and Heroes
Will the dice that Balsa rolls
come up good luck or bad?